Finding Aid for Raymond J. Smit Papers 1960-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Raymond J. Smit Papers 1960-1977
Smith, Raymond J., 1928-
Republican member of the Michigan House of Representatives. Legislative files, 1967-1974, concerning in part his interest in water pollution legislation; political files concerning election campaigns, and involvement in Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County, Michigan, Republican Party activities; and photographs.
85408 Aa 2
20 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The major portion of the collection was received in 1975. A smaller addition came in 1982. Donor no. 5764.
The collection is open for research.
Raymond J. Smit was born on September 21, 1928 in Detroit, Michigan. He received degrees in civil engineering (B.A., 1950; M. A., 1955) from the University of Michigan. Upon graduation, he took a position at Ayres, Lewis, Norris, and May, a firm of consulting engineers, Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Raymond Smit's political activities began in the late 1950s when he became involved in Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County Republican affairs. From 1958 to 1962, he worked for the campaign committees of various Republican candidates for local offices, and served as director of Ann Arbor's Fifth Ward Republican Committee. In December 1962, he became chairman of the Ann Arbor Republican Committee, and served in that position until May 1965. In addition, he served on the Ann Arbor Housing and Zoning Board of Appeals from 1961 to 1966. As a reward for his service to the party, Smit was chosen to be an alternate delegate to the 1964 Republican National Convention.
Raymond Smit was first elected to the Michigan House of Representatives in 1966 from the 53rd district, which then consisted of Ann Arbor city and township. Subsequently, he was re-elected in 1968 and 1970. In 1972, he was elected from the newly altered 52nd district which included only a small portion of Ann Arbor along with new territory added to the district primarily in eastern Washtenaw County.
As a State Representative, Raymond Smith served on the following House Standing Committees: Conservation, Environment, and Recreation; State Affairs; Colleges and Universities; Economic Development; and Roads and Bridges. During his years in office, he sponsored and authored legislation relating to his various committee assignments. Legislation in the area of air and water pollution control was his primary interest. In 1968, he was the chief sponsor of Michigan's pollution control bond issue. The bond issue, once approved by the voters of Michigan, was implemented through enactment of new laws and amendments or revisions of existing statutes.
Smit was also the prime sponsor of what was dubbed as the "Truth in Water Pollution" bill that initiated a new concept of pollution surveillance. Through this legislation, industry was to pay the cost of monitoring its uses of state water resources. In 1974, Smit retired from the State House in order to pursue his career in civil engineering.
The Raymond Smit collection consists entirely of materials generated during his eight years in the Michigan House of Representatives, 1967-1974. The series in the collection are Legislative files which consists of subject files and bills files; Personal Materials; Political Files (1960-1975); Legislative Special Topics Files (1967-1974); and Photographs
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Elections--Michigan--1968.; Elections--Michigan--1970.; Elections--Michigan--1972.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Republican Party (Mich.); Smit, Raymond J., 1928-; Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Water.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Cement industries--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Cement industries.; Detroit (Mich.)--Industrial buildings.; Industrial buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Interiors.; Madison Heights (Mich.); Madison Heights (Mich.)--Waterworks.; Michigan. Legislature.; Peerless Cement Company (Detroit, Mich.); Political elections.; Red Run Drain (Mich.); Smit, Raymond J., 1928-; Waterworks--Michigan--Madison Heights.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Legislative File
  The principal series - Legislative files - is arranged at first by single year and then by two-year term. This series is further divided into two categories of materials. One of these is a set of numbered files arranged for the most part by department within the state government. These files contain a variety of documents, such as correspondence with fellow legislators, constituents, and lobbying groups, as well as office memos, reports, and relevant background information on a particular issue. The following is a list of the headings (with the corresponding file number) used by Smit and his staff.
  Administration, Dept. of [file no. 1]
  Agriculture, Dept. of [file no. 2]
  Attorney General [file no. 3]
  Auditor General [file no. 4]
  Civil Rights, Dept. of [file no. 5]
  Civil Service, Dept. of [file no. 6]
  Commerce, Dept. of [file no. 7]
  Corrections, Dept. of [file no. 8]
  Education, Dept. of [file no. 9]
  Labor, Dept. of [file no. 10]
  Licensing and Regulation, Dept. of [file no. 11]
  Mental Health, Dept. of [file no. 12]
  Military Affairs, Dept. of [file no. 13]
  Natural Resources, Dept. of [file no. 14]
  Public Health, Dept. of [file no. 15]
  Social Services, Dept. of [file no. 16]
  State, Dept. of [file no. 17]
  State Highways, Dept. of [file no. 18]
  State Police, Dept. of [file no. 19]
  Treasury, Dept. of [file no. 20]
  Executive Department [file no. 21]
  Judiciary [file no. 22]
  Legislative Affairs [file no. 23]
  Local Government [file no. 24]
  National Affairs [file no. 25]
  Republican Party [file no. 26]
  Speeches [file no. 27]
  Personal [file no. 28]
  The second category of files within the Legislative file is Smit's Bills File. These files are arranged by legislative session and include background information, committee reports, and correspondence. They are further arranged in order of the assigned bill number.
  - 1967-1974 bills file (Box 20)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 2)
  - 1968 (Box 2)
  - 1968 (Box 3)
  - 1969 (numbered files, 7-9) (Box 3)
  - 1969 (numbered files, 9-14) (Box 4)
  - 1969 (numbered files, 14-25) (Box 5)
  - 1969 (numbered files, 26-29) (Box 6)
  - 1970 (numbered files, 3-9) (Box 6)
  - 1970 (numbered files, 9-18) (Box 7)
  - 1970 (numbered files, 18-28) (Box 8)
  - 1971-1972 (numbered files, 2-9) (Box 8)
  - 1971-1972 (numbered files, 9-15) (Box 9)
  - 1971-1972 (numbered files, 16-26) (Box 10)
  - 1971-1972 (bills file) (Box 10)
  - 1971-1972 (bills file) (Box 11)
  - 1971-1972 (bills file) (Box 12)
  - 1973-1974 Committee on Conservation, Environment, and Recreation (Box 12)
  - 1973-1974 Committee to Study Northwestern Highway Extension (Box 12)
  - 1973-1974 (numbered files, 1-7) (Box 12)
  - 1973-1974 (numbered files, 8-14) (Box 13)
  - 1973-1974 (numbered files, 14-23) (Box 14)
  - 1973-1974 (numbered files, 24-28) (Box 15)
  - 1973-1974 (bills file) (Box 15)
  - 1973-1974 (bills file) (Box 16)
- Personal materials
  The Personal Materials are mainly biographical sketches and clippings about Smit's life and career.
  - Biographical Sketches and news clippings (Box 16)
- Political files 1960-1975
  Political Files has two subseries based on geographical areas: Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County Files, and State and National Files. The Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County files provide some insight Into Smit's early political career on behalf of local Republican organizations. The State and National subseries relates to Smit's political activities while in the Michigan House of Representatives. Some of the more important files included in this subseries concern Smit's campaigns for election, his retirement announcement in 1974, his being considered for a position in the Environmental Protection Agency (1973), and his activities on behalf of former Governor William Milliken. The kinds of material found in the political files include correspondence, news clippings, reports, and texts of speeches.
  - Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County
    - City Hall Bond Issue 1960 (Box 16)
    - Civil Rights and Fair Housing Laws 1963 (Box 16)
    - Lakewood Street Improvements 1960 (Box 16)
    - Letter to University of Michigan President, March 30, 1970 (Box 20)
    - Republican Committee (Ann Arbor) 1960-1964
      - Elections 1960-1964
        - Spring 1960 (Box 16)
        - Fall 1960 (Box 16)
        - Spring 1961 (Box 16)
        - Spring 1962 (Box 16)
        - Fall 1962 (Box 16)
        - Spring 1963, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Spring 1964, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Fall 1964, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Finances 1961-1962 (Box 17)
      - Platforms 1961-1963 (Box 17)
      - Social Activities 1962-1963 (Box 17)
      - Structure/Organization 1962 (Box 17)
    - Republican Committee (Washtenaw County) 1963-1965, 1974
      - Conventions 1964
        - March 1964 (Box 17)
        - September 1964 (Box 17)
      - Papers (general) 1962-1965 (Box 17)
      - Papers (general) 1974 (Box 17)
    - School Board 1963-1964 (Box 17)
  - State and National
    - Citizens for Michigan 1961 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1973-1974 (Box 17)
    - Environmental news articles, 1969 (Box 20)
    - Environmental Protection Agency 1973 (Box 17)
    - Great Lakes Shoreland Conference 1974, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Griffin, Robert P. (Senate Campaign Committee) 1972 (Box 17)
    - Michigan House of Representatives
      - Election Campaign Files
        - 1968 Campaign
          - Announcement (Box 17)
          - Finances (Box 17)
          - Lists (Box 17)
          - Parties (Box 17)
          - Publicity (Box 17)
          - Support (Box 20)
        - 1970 Campaign
          - Certificate of election and news articles (Box 20)
          - Lists (Box 17)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
          - Papers (general) (Box 17)
          - Petitions (Box 17)
          - Support (Box 20)
        - 1972 Campaign
          - Analysis (Box 18)
          - Announcement (Box 18)
          - Campaign Committee (Box 18)
          - Campus Advisory Committee (Box 18)
          - Finances (Box 18)
          - Lists (Box 18)
          - Papers (general), 2 folders (Box 18)
          - Questionnaires (Box 18)
          - Publicity (Box 18)
      - Office Hours and District Tours 1973-1974 (Box 18)
      - Press Releases 1967-1968 (Box 18)
      - Retirement Announcement 1974 (Box 18)
      - Social Events 1969-1974
        - Legislative Dinners 1969-1974 (Box 18)
        - Lame Duck Party 1974 (Box 18)
    - Milliken, William L. (Governor)
      - Campaign Committee 1974 (Box 18)
      - Speech before U.S. House of Representatives Subcommittee on Water Resources, Public Works Committee 1973 (Box 18)
    - Newsletters--Legislative Reports, 1968-1974 (Box 20)
    - Portage Lake 1974 (Box 18)
    - Position papers
      - 1964-1967 (Box 20)
      - Super Sewer Controversy,1974-1977 (Box 20)
    - Press--news articles
      - 1969-1974, 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Press releases
      - 1968-1974, 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Republican National Convention Alternate Delegate 1964 (Box 18)
    - Romney, George W. (Governor)
      - State Appointments 1963-1964 (Box 18)
      - Task Force on Water Rights, Use, and Pollution Control 1965 (Box 18)
    - Speeches 1965-1975
      - 1965-1966 (Box 18)
      - 1967-1971 (Box 18)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 18)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 18)
      - Discharge motion on sen 3, June 15, 1971 (Box 20)
        (cassette tape)
- Legislative special topics files 1967-1974
  The Legislative special topics files mainly concern the pollution control bond issue. They are generally arranged alphabetically by subject for each specific legislative session.
  - 1967 Session, Conflict of Interest (Box 18)
  - 1968 Session
    - Clean Water Bond Issue (Box 18)
    - Sewage Treatment Facilities, HB 2646 (Box 18)
    - Water Pollution Finance Study Committee, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1969 Session
    - Clean Water Bond Issue
      - Legislation (grants for Sewage Treatment Facilities)
        - HB 2097 (Box 19)
        - HB 2098 (Box 19)
        - HB 2282-2288 (Box 19)
        - SB 107 (Box 19)
      - Outline of Clean Water Bond Program (Box 19)
    - Inland Lake Improvement Act Amendment (Box 19)
  - 1970 Session
    - Clean Water Bond Issue
      - General Papers and Statistics (Box 19)
      - Manistee Lake (Box 19)
      - Water Resources Commission, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - 1971-1972 Sessions
    - Special Legislative Committee on Peerless Cement Company, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - 1973 Session
    - Conflict of Interest (Joint Committee Transcript) (Box 19)
    - Ecorse Creek, HR 618 (Box 19)
  - 1974 Session
    - Bills, Reports, and Papers 1974, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Republican House Office (Summary of Legislation) (Box 19)
    - Waste Disposal on State Lands (Box 19)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits; and photographs of Michigan industries and waterways, notably the Peerless Cement Company in Detroit and Red Run Drain in Madison Heights.
  - Highways and waterways (Box 19)
  - Industry (Box 19)
  - Legislative groups (Box 19)
  - Peerless Cement Co. (Box 19)
  - Platte River dedication, 1974 (Box 20)
  - Political colleagues (Box 20)
  - Portraits (Box 19)
  - Republican press (Box 20)
  - Romney, George (Box 19)
  - Water pollution bond bill signing--SB 107, 1969 (Box 20)